

About me

IT professional with 14+ years of experience. In the last 10 years I have been specialized in the Business Intelligence area, working in the financial, insurance and the manufactured industry. Industries where I have been participated in many projects as Data Architecture Role, Head of Data Warehouse and Business Intelligence Role, Data Analyst Role and Data Engineer Role, which is the one that I am performing.

Work Experience

Data Engineer, BairesDev, United States

MARCH 2022 — AT PRESENT

- Create and maintain data pipelines using Python.
- Build entire data lifecycle using AWS Infrastructure and Managed Services like MWAA, S3 and Redshift.
- Extract large datasets from websites and ingest the data into datalakes.

Business Intelligence & Data Engineer, BOWPI, Guatemala

JUNE 2021 — AT PRESENT(FREELANCE)

- Work in the entire lifecycle of the BI projects in BOWPI.
- Extract and organize the automatic collection of data in different formats (structured and no structured data).
- Secure the Data Warehouse service in the Redshift Database.
- Design Dashboards or Reports using Tableau or Superset.

Head of Data Warehouse & Business Intelligence, Multigroup, Guatemala

AUGUST 2019 — JUNE 2021

- Lead the Multigroup BI projects.
- Plan and organize the automatic collection of data.
- Secure the Data Warehouse Service in the PostgreSQL Database.
- Dimensional Data Modeling from SAP S4/HANA.
- Design Dashboards and Reports using Data Visualization Tools like Power BI and Tableau.

Business Intelligence Coordinator, Seguros G&T, S.A., Guatemala

MAY 2010 — AUGUST 2019

- Coordinate the BI projects, having a team of 6 members.
- Secure the Company ETL and Data services in the Data Warehouse.
 Giving the stakeholders the availability to make data-driven decisions.
- Work with data mining tools in analytical and strategic projects.
- Transform the data in reports, dashboards and KPIs who can ensure the data-driven decisions in the company for all the managers and stakeholders
- Secure the availability of the Managers Dashboards using Data Visualization tools like Tableau and Oracle BI.

Information

Guatemala, Guatemala (502) 54609667 melvin1020@gmail.com

04-14-1988

Links to social media

LinkedIn

Skills

Business Intelligence

Effective Communication

Strategic Planning

Leadership

Python for Data Science

Data Analysis

Data Visualization

Data Engineering

Relational and No SQL Database

Hobbies

Travel Sports History

Languages

English

Spanish

Education

Master of Business Administration, Mariano Galvez University, Guatemala

AUGUST 2018

· Third Quarter Finished

Bachelor of System Administration Engineer, Mariano Galvez University, Guatemala

FEBRUARY 2007 — MAY 2011

Courses

Business Intelligence, Pontificia Universidad Javeriana de Colombia

APRIL 2014 — DECEMBER 2014

Engineering Project Management PMBOK Standard, USAC

SEPTEMBER 2016 — SEPTEMBER 2016

Python for Data Science, UVG EDUCON

FEBRUARY 2019 — FEBRUARY 2021

Alteryx Introduction, Computing Resources

JULY 2018 — JULY 2018

Learn Power BI Fast, Udemy

APRIL 2020 — APRIL 2020

Machine Learning Introduction, UVG EDUCON

JULY 2019 — JULY 2021

Tableau 2021 A-Z: Hands-On Tableau Training for Data Science, Udemy

MARCH 2021 — HASTA LA FECHA

Scrum Master, ScrumStudy

JANUARY 2019 — FEBRUARY 2021

Personal References

Eder Meléndez from Seguros G&T, S.A.

emelendez@gyt.com.gt · 5413-3192

Sergio Alonzo from All Data Consulting

sergio.alonzo@gmail.com · 5067-4361

Noé Gualim from Credito Hipotecario Nacional

ageon@gmail.com · 4149-9120